Guide to the Abraham Gitlow Papers MC.27
New York University Archives
Abraham Gitlow Papers
1920-1994
1950-1994
New York University Archives
Gitlow, Abraham L. (Abraham Leo), 1918-2014
MC.27
6 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons and two manuscript boxes
43 Reels 7" open reel audiotapes
Abraham L. Gitlow was born in New York City in 1918. Gitlow served as a professor of Economics at New York University (NYU) until 1965, when he became Dean of what is now NYU's Leonard N. Stern School of Business. He retired from his position as Dean in 1985, and continued as Dean Emeritus and Professor of Economics Emeritus at the Stern School until his death in 2014. The collection contains his articles, correspondence, minutes, drafts, plus event sound recordings from his tenure at NYU.
Access Restrictions
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact New York University Archives, (212) 998-2646, university-archives@nyu.edu.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
University Archives Biographical Files, "Gitlow, A.L."
University Archives Portrait Files, "Gitlow, Abraham"
For more information about the Leonard N. Stern School of Business, see the Records of the Office of the Dean of the School of Commerce and the School of Business and Public Administration, RG 27, in University Archives.
Historical Note
The Leonard N. Stern School of Business was founded in 1900 by Charles Waldo Haskins as the New York University (NYU) Undergraduate School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance at NYU's Washington Square Campus. The graduate business program was launched in 1916. Located in New York's downtown business district, it offered both full-time and part-time professional degree programs.
The School of Commerce, Accounts and Finance was renamed the College of Business and Public Administration and merged with the Graduate School of Business and Public Administration in 1972. The same year, the school's Tisch Hall opened to house the undergraduate college.
In 1988 NYU Business School alumnus Leonard Stern donated $30 million. The school was renamed the Leonard N. Stern School of Business (Stern School of Business) in his honor. The gift allowed the school to consolidate its graduate and undergraduate facilities to NYU's Washington Square campus. The Kaufman Management Center later opened in 1992 as a state-of-the-art facility for the Stern School.
Biographical Note
Abraham L. Gitlow was born in New York City in 1918. He received his bachelor's degree from the University of Pennsylvania in 1939, and his masters and doctoral degrees from Columbia University in 1940 and 1947, respectively. From 1943 to 1946 he served in the U.S. Army Air Forces in the South Pacific as an assistant historical officer. After World War II, Gitlow was a substitute instructor in economics at Brooklyn College. He left Brooklyn College in 1947 to teach economics at New York University (NYU). Gitlow served as a professor of economics at NYU until 1965, when he became the dean of NYU's School of Commerce, which would become the Stern School of Business. He retired from the position of dean of the College of Business Administration in 1985 and continued as Dean Emeritus and Professor of Economics Emeritus at the Stern School until his death in 2014. Gitlow married Beatrice Alpert in 1940. They had two sons, Allan Michael and Howard Seth.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Abraham Gitlow's professional papers from 1955 to 1994, primarily from his time as Dean of the NYU Stern School of Business from 1965 to 1985. Professional materials include information and correspondence regarding the Charles C. Moskowitz lectures and publications (1973-1980), Annual School of Commerce Alumni Dinner (1965-1985), NYU Finance Club (1985), Madden Memorial Award (1980-1985), audio recordings of Dean's Day and other lectures, and NYU Club correspondence, minutes and financial statements (1967-1971).
This collection also includes correspondence, drafts, and final copies of Gitlow's printed articles. It also contains drafts, letters, and editorial notes for Gitlow's NYU'S Stern School of Business: A Centennial Retrospective.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series, with Series I in two subseries:
Missing Title
Alumni Relations
Publications and Course Materials
All-University
The Stern Story Drafts, Research Materials
College of Business and Public Administration event and lecture recordings
Separated Materials
Materials from Accession #81.055 were separated or transferred to other collections and include: 43 open reel audio tapes, NYU Design Standards Manual to RG 7.2.3, 250 slides of Commerce activities to the Photo Collection, correspondence regarding dedication of Tisch Hall to the Collection on New York University Buildings, box 16, folder3; and an alumni fundraising scrapbook to RG 40.27. Audio tapes were reintegrated December 2018 as Series V: College of Business and Public Administration event and lecture recordings.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact New York University Archives, (212) 998-2646, university-archives@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Records were transferred to University Archives by the Office of the Dean, Stern School of Business, from 1981 through 1995.
Minutes (administrative records); New York (N.Y.).; Lectures and lecturing.; Correspondence.; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Labor unions; Universities and Colleges -- Business management; Universities and Colleges -- Administration; Business Education; 20th century.; Universities and Colleges -- Alumni and alumnae.; Publishers and publishing; New York University. Graduate School of Business Administration; New York University. School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance; New York University -- Special Events; New York University -- Fundraising; New York University -- Faculty -- History; New York University -- Washington Square Campus
- Series I: Stern School of Business Alumni Relations, 1972-1986; 2.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains materials pertaining to NYU's Stern School of Business alumni reunions, dinners, awards ceremonies, and other events.
  - Subseries I: Events
    - Class of 1942 Reunions, 1977, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Commerce Dinner Remarks 5/8/85 and Timetable Photo List, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1960s Group, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Commerce Annual Dinner - 25th Annual Reunion Committee Meeting, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1985-86 Class of 1927 Dues (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Class of 1927 Annual Dinner 9/28/83, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Class of 1949 35th Reunion, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Commerce Dinner 5/8/85 Planning, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Commerce Dinner 5/8/85 Attendees, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Commerce Dinner 1982, 1983, 1984, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Class of '35 50th Anniversary Dinner, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Commerce Dinner 1985 Menus, etc., 1969, 1973, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Commerce Annual Dinner 5/8/84 Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 50th Reunion Lunch - Class of '36, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Class of 1964 20th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Class of 1969 15th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Class of 1974 Contact Lists, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Class of 1974 10th Reunion, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Class of 1979 5th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Fund Workers 1984, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Alumni Fund Workers Kits, 1984-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Memoranda to 1980-81 Fund Workers (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Commerce Alumni Association Officers and Directors 1985-86, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Alumni Federation Meritorious Service Award, 1976-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Committee 1985-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - NYU Finance Club Forms and Letters, Originals, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Memos from Amanda, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Commerce Class of 1933 Reunion Committee 1983 (Commerce Annual Dinner), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Class of 1957 Reunion Committee Meeting - 3/25/82, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Class of 1957 Reunion 5/5/82, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Class of 1939 45th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Class of 1954 45th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Commerce Photos Class of 1934 50th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Class of 1927 Reunion - 10/12/82, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Class of 1927 Annual Dinner 9/10/81, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Class of 1929 50th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Class of 1927 Annual Dues: 1982-83, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Class of 1927 Annual Dues: 1981-1982, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Class of 1914 70th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Class of 1917 Reunions, 1981-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Class of 1924 60th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Class of 1927 Dinner Reunion 12/5/1985 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Edward Jaworski Correspondence 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Edward Jaworski Correspondence 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Commerce Annual Dinner Letters 5/8/85 - Folder 1 of 4, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Commerce Annual Dinner Letter 5/8/85 - Folder 2 of 4, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Commerce Annual Dinner Letters 5/8/85 - Folder 3 of 4, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Commerce Annual Dinner Letters 5/8/85 - Folder 4 of 4, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Class of 1927 Dues 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Commerce Class of 1927 Annual Meeting 11/1/84, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Commerce Class of 1927 Dues 1983-84, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Postage Report, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Pink Copies 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Commerce Annual Dinner 5/8/85 Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Commerce Dinner 1985 Invitees, 1983-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Dinner Billing Information, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Commerce Annual Dinner 5/8/85, 1958, 1965-1968, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Commerce Dinner 5/8/85 (Samples of Letters to Classes Done by Holzer), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Commerce Dinner Declinations 5/8/85, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Alumni Federation, 1985-86, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Madden Memorial Award 1980, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Madden Memorial Award Yellow Copies 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Madden Memorial Award Originals 1984-1985, 1984-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Commerce Dinner 5/8/85 Agendas, Lists, Gitlow Bio Information, 1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Alumni Federation Dinner 1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Resume of Alumni Federation Services to the Commerce Alumni Assoc. and the Financial Club, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Clark Foundation, 1972-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Gifts and Pledges (Office of Development), 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Suberies II: Correspondence
    - Haskins and Sells Scholarship, 1955, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Japanese Accountant Seminar Aug. 4-7 1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Japanese August Seminar Materials, 1969, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Japanese Accountants August 11-12 1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Madden Awards 1973-75, 1974-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - J.K. Lasser Institute, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Sponsored Research and Training Programs Manual and Related Materials, 1967, 1969, 1971, 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 75th Anniversary (1975), 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Applied Science Degree Program Brochure, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Portraits, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Seidman and Seidman Commerce Reading Room, 1964-1967, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Key Issues Lecture Series, 1973-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Moskowitz Lecture 3/9/77 - Folder 1 of 3, 1973, 1976-78 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Moskowitz Lecture 3/9/77 - Folder 2 of 3, 1973, 1976-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Moskowitz Lecture 3/9/77 - Folder 3 of 3, 1973, 1976-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - SEHNAP Master List Fall 1987 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - President's Advisory Council to BPA - Meeting of 11/30/72, 1972, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Madden Associates 1971, 1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Moskowitz 1978, 1974-1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Moskowitz Lecture 1979, 1978-1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Moskowitz Lecture 1979 - Publications, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Moskowitz Publications 1975-1976, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series II: Publications and Course Materials, 1950-1984; 1 Linear Feet in one record carton
  Series II contains articles by Gitlow and student papers, exams, evaluations, and other documents from business school courses.
  - "American Trade Unions and Politics", circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "The National Wage Policy: Antecedents and Application", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "The Trade Union Prospect in the Coming Decade", 1969-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Social Legislation & the Stagflation Trap", 1977-1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Comments on Labor & Manpower Economics - 3rd Edition, RDI, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Growth of Public Employee Unionism", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Are Peacetime Wage-Price Controls Effective?", 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "The Future of Undergraduate Business Education", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "The American Business School: Trends and Challenges", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Economics Seen Darkly in a Political Mirror", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Are Peacetime Wage-Price Controls Effective?" - Italian publication, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Women in the American Economy: Today & Tomorrow", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Will Recession Beat Inflation?" - Delivered to Faculty Women's Club, 1980 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "The Wage Price Situation" - The Commercial and Financial Chronicle, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Union Management Relations: An Important Piece of the Quality Puzzle", undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Labor and Manpower Economics outlines, 1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - B30.4201 Labor Economics: Wages - outline, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - B20.2381 Labor Economics: Wages - student papers, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - B05.2403 Business Economics - final exams, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - B30.2281 Labor Economics: Wages - final exams, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - B05.2403 Business Economics - final exams, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - B30.2201 Economic Analysis - final exams, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Extracts from Thesis of S.K. Burnell, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Series III: All-University, 1955-1985; .5 Linear Feet in one record carton
  Series III contains NYU Club records and other business school documents.
  - NYU Club: Correspondence, By-Laws, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - NYU Club: Minutes, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - NYU Club: Financial Statements, 1966 June-September (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - NYU Club: Financial Statements, 1966 October-December (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - NYU Club: Financial Statements, 1967 January-May (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - NYU Club: Financial Statements, 1967 June-September (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - NYU Club: Financial Statements, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Updated Standard Form Letters, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Schools of Business Ad Hoc Committee, 1955-1966, 1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Engineering and Science, 1965-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Photograph of Charles C. Moskowitz, Hon. Hubert H. Humphrey, U.S. Senator and former VP, Dean A.L. Gittow on the occasion of Senator Humphrey's delivery of the Moskowitz Lecture, Young America in the New World, undated (Box Shared University Archives 042, Folder 22)
- Series IV: The Stern Story Drafts, Research Materials, 1920-1994; .5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
  Series IV contains drafts, reports, correspondence, and other materials for Gitlow's history of the Stern School of Business.
  - Annual Reports and Xeroxes - Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports and Xeroxes - Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sam Shapiro's Editing Suggestions, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Stern Story Letters, etc., 1971, 1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Business School & Technology 1987-1994, 1987, 1990, 1993-1994, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Stern Story Draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - NYU Financial Data, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - GBA Faculty Minutes 1920-1923, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series V: College of Business and Public Administration event and lecture recordings, 1972-1976, undated; 2 Linear Feet in two record cartons (Box 6, Box 7)
  Series V consists of sound recordings of the Ross Institute, Dean's Day, Tisch Hall dedication ceremonies, the School of Commerce ITT lectures, the College of Business and Public Administration lectures, and the School of Commerce Conference lectures on Women in Careers.